That's one thing that people would
really struggle to understand when we
say like the in order to enter the first
Janna you factually have to
uh give up even the liability to the
five hindrances not just like specific
manifestations because then it would
sound like also you're saying you have
to basically become an ar in order to
enter the first genre but the thing
is yeah the liability to the hindrances
is factual gone at that time whether you
like it or not. But that doesn't mean
that uh they will not come
back. Because if you incline the mind,
if you if
you give in to the things that at that
time don't feel like they're a problem,
the hindrances will return.
So I thought we could
discuss mindfulness from the perspective
mindfulness from the perspective
of losing mindfulness. That's it because
we already talked in the past about the
porcupatas and
and
um to some extent we discussed the
hindrances and and things like that but
it was more in a broader level.
So I think first of all we could start
by
defining what is mindfulness because
when many people hear that word they
might confuse it with a momentto moment
focused awareness and for that very
reason they wouldn't necessarily
realize how they lose it because they
would think that you
know if if if I just if I can just
um focus more, focus harder, not have
any external
circumstances bothering me and things
like that. Then I'll be able to maintain
my mindfulness in like a 10day protected
retreat environment and then not
realize what is it that actually
constitutes mindfulness and how to
protect it. So Mhm. how could we define
mindfulness in a more accurate
way or not necessarily focusing on the
angle of mindfulness? You could also
call it samadei or composure because it
it goes hand in hand
like solidified mindfulness is is
basically the same as composure being
established. So um experientially how does it feel to
So um experientially how does it feel to
have
um mindfulness established? That's it.
Mhm. still
calm. That's a result of the mindfulness
because you can
be still or calm actually from use your
lack of mindfulness as well.
Yes. Having a perspective upon the
situation. Yeah, that would be one way.
But is that
perspective something that you are kind
of actively maintaining?
Well, the right mindfulness is based on
understanding what is already there
given. Um, and so the mindfulness is the
Um, and so the mindfulness is the
recollection or the remembering of those
aspects of your experience that have to
be there already. Um, and so those
things you don't need to maintain. M um
but then the question is or I think this
is what you're asking like so one can
recollect those things which are like
satipana or death or or auba or any
context that you set up that is the
direction of the right mindfulness but
then that context or the perspective can
be lost. So we're working towards
finding out what what are the factors
that run force away from that context
but but those things that you were
established in in of themselves they
don't go anywhere. Yeah. But at the same
time the mindness itself the perspective
over those
things. Is it something you do or is it
something that
or is it not something you do?
So can you so let's put it this way. Um,
can you just say that it's already
there? Because if if you just say it
like that, then it sounds like you don't
have to do anything and we're already
enlightened or something. Well, no. Um,
that's clearly not the meaning here. But
yeah, so you do need to
understand those aspects or principles
to begin with because otherwise you
can't correctly recollect them and that
and it won't be the right perspective
and you do in a sense need to set it up.
But if you do that properly then in a
sense your mindfulness will be there on
its own. But it's not going to be like
that from the beginning. So there is an
aspect of understanding and there is an
aspect of establishing and then you have
to just let it endure on its own. And
then the question is how are we going to
find out once it's been lost. Yeah. But
so the the point I'm trying to highlight
is that when mindfulness is established
um because it's important to recognize
it's not something you do.
um you you have to work to clarify it
and and understand it as you said or
once it's there um it's it's kind of
there on its own independ it's
containing you in a way. Yes. not it's
not something that you are doing. And
um that is actually precisely one of the
reasons why if you're not careful you
will lose
it because it feels like you don't need
to maintain it anymore. Precisely
because of that
factual fact in a sense you don't need
to maintain it anymore but you overlook
that there are things that you will that
you could do that will slowly degrade.
Yeah. Make it you built up.
So, um, but what so you said it's it's a
perspective, but is it a perspective of
something specific? Is it like
um a specific thought that endures in
your mind or is
it something
else? Well, the the perspective is of
the totality quote unquote of this
experience. Um so that is part of the understanding
Um so that is part of the understanding
right so as we discussed with the
satipana that there are four let's
sayological totalities so they all um
they're slightly different fantas points
but they disclose your experience as a
whole that is that would be the right
mindfulness if it's not like that and
you're going to focus on something
specific it will it will always be as we
that many times in front of you. Then
you try to focus on that very hard and
then the whole question of distraction
comes in like you know there's going to
be a conflict between looking at that
class and a particular thought arising
and I feel I need to suppress it because
I want to focus on the thing there and
then all of that comes along which
actually has nothing really to do with
what we're talking about now. So, so
assuming that that wrong direction is
out of the way um then the then the
mindfulness is about
understanding this situation as a whole.
Yeah. But is there a specific is it that
the mindfulness is a it has a specific
theme um tied to it or is it something that's
um tied to it or is it something that's
not linked to a specific theme? Like if
you choose to develop mindfulness of
feelings, is it that just feelings is
what come comes up for your perspective
only and then if you want to be mindful
of something else, you have to change
your object. Is that how it works or well no?
object. Is that how it works or well no?
Well, if you have discerned feeling on
that most general level, then your
mindfulness can be there like there will
be mindfulness with feeling and then
within that all sorts of other things
can take place. But that will not be in
conflict with being mindful of that
general feeling because yeah. So what
what I'm pointing at is mindfulness is
uh kind of
um it's a quality in and of
itself and it's it's not defined by it's
just the broadening of perspective.
Mindfulness you could say is the
broadening of perspective. And it
doesn't matter whether that broadening
of perspective is
um kind of
uh instantiated through perspective of
the body, perspective of feelings,
perspective of mind, perspective of
phenomena. If you have developed that
mindfulness properly on the right level,
any of these four things you could take
up for reflection with the same
mindfulness that you've built up. Mhm.
So in other words, it's just like um
space, let's say space that opens up and
then that space can be filled in with
any any basically anything you that
takes your fancy. Uh, and that's that's
another the reason why I'm bringing that
up is because that dispels the whole
notion of it being about locking your
mind into one specific thing cuz you can
you can think of it as in on a very
wrong extremely wrong level of of
thinking of it as a as a specific object
of of concentrated focus. Mhm. But uh
even if you start thinking about it as a
as a context or a theme or reflection,
you might also still have some lingering
notion that it's about like maintain
like keeping those spec keeping your
mind within that specific topic. Mhm. Um
and it's not necessarily the case. Like
the mindfulness is just the ability,
it's just the perspective. That's it.
the ability to see your experience for
what it is at any given time. It's just
a sense of clarity and
um
so having said that then
um how is it that you would lose it?
Because if it's not about keeping it
tied to the same theme even, it's not
that I'll need to be thinking about
feelings the whole evening in order to
develop mindfulness. Like I said, it's
it's a direction. So you could cultivate
it in multiple different ways. So um how
is it that you would lose it given that
it's it's not tied to a specific
thing. Not tied to a specific thing, but
clearly it it does get lost. It's not
that it's just like once you uh
establish my friends properly, that's
it. You're done and you become
Did you lose
anyone? By accepting the light and entertaining and entertaining
[Music]
that relief
that other sensuality or let's say doubt
for example present you with.
So generally it would begin with like
subtler things or like minor things but
then each time you kind of prioritize
that relief you are
relief you are
basically sliding away and and why is it
why does it present itself as relief if
you're kind of already clear about the
fact that that's not where relief comes
from. Why why would you still give
in if the mindfulness it's clear I know
that this is to to a certain extent you
might already be experiencing
experiencing the right type of relief of
giving up of perspective of dispassion
why is it still why would you still yeah
well because of the habit basically okay
yeah that's on a broader scale but at
that moment Like what is it that makes
you okay discomfort?
But if you seeing that discomfort as not
yours as something that arose on its own
because your mindfulness established
then why do why would you still do it?
I don't think you would if you saw it
the way it's written. Okay. But what I'm
saying, you could have the clarity that
oh this is arisen on its own. This is
not mine. This is impermanent and all
this stuff and yet you would get it
cuz you wouldn't see the thing. Uh sure.
Uh sure.
But like if you the thing is like we
said before the mindfulness is not even
something that you actively do. So in a
way the clarity that it is dangerous
that it is impermanent that it is
suffering that it is not yours that
clarity would be enduring there even
like regardless of what you do even if
you don't actively think about oh this
is this is dangerous you you know that
it's dangerous because the mindfulness
is intelligent on that peripheral level.
So given that
that's despite the fact that's there,
you would give in
what just being careless and again
prioritizing the wrong Yeah. thing.
That's that's as as close as you can
get. It's just carelessness. Like
there's it's not that you don't know
that it's um not the right direction.
You you know that it is but uh the
carelessness is in a way
um by putting the wrong emphasis on like
cuz see you could take it either way.
You could take it as when you when you
have that clarity and it feels like you
know everything is is um you see things
as they are as the Buddha would say. It
can feel as if okay so it doesn't matter
what I do then because this clarity is
going to be there anyway
but you could take that in two
directions it doesn't matter what I do
therefore I would break my restraint and
give into the hindrances and factually
the clarity will not fade away
immediately because it kind of precedes
the domain of action
or you could take it the other way and
say well it doesn't matter what what I
do so let me not do it let me not give
in and Um but the thing is it's like the
clarity the domain of the mind in
general it's it's not some it's always
indirect it's not something that you can
kind of measure like this is how much
mindfulness I have so what you would do
is like you would give in and uh you
kind of check okay it's I haven't lost
it it's still there it's still there so
you feel like okay well it doesn't
matter let me just fully go wild and uh
and later on you would look back and you
realize oh
It's gone now. Mhm. Abruptly, you just
realized, oh, wait, it's gone. You
didn't even see um there there was no
warning sign. There was nothing. In the
same way that there was no warning sign
when you were developing it properly,
you suddenly realize, oh wait, I've been
I've been like as as that says like
wearing down the axe handles have been
wearing it down and suddenly you
realize, oh now I cannot even forget
that things are impermanent that the
body comes first all these things. Okay,
now mindfulness is established.
So
um so yeah it works both ways. So that's
why it's it's important to to to be
clear that it's that dimension that
doesn't depend on you because then first
that would allow you to develop it
properly and secondly it would also
allow you to protect it because if if
you're still putting the emphasis on
um
like your kind of aspect of the equation
you would forget that actually there's
there's a like you may not feel any
problem with doing with doing these
things u that go against the direction
they develop but um there is that kind
of a delayed effect that these things
will lead to and it always snowballs. So
the more you give in the the kind of
easier it gets to continue that
direction.
So, and what is it that you would give
into specifically because let's say somebody
specifically because let's say somebody
you might not not even break the
precepts um it would be assumed that you
know if you even got to the point where
your mindfulness is well established you
were already established in virtue. So
why is it that despite not breaking the
precepts, you would still um lose your
mind? Well, it has to start with mental
Well, it has to start with mental
action, right?
Like you're not going to act out by body
unless you've been welcoming thoughts
related to acting out by body.
And that's more subtle than breaking the
precepts. And it can almost like not to say that
And it can almost like not to say that
it's like accidental but well I guess if
you are mindful you can't overlook it.
If you are properly mindful, you won't
overlook it. But kind of like you
say, you can just kind of see it as oh
well, you
know, this is insignificant. That's
another point. Is it accidental? Because
I think there's often this perception
that um people are do kind of get a sense of,
um people are do kind of get a sense of,
oh yeah, I've developed this clarity
because I've been doing this 10day
retreat. And then they would still have
the sense that when they go back it's
kind of like because of the external
world and because of the situations that
that they have to
face those external things are making
them lose their mindfulness
accidentally. So
So
um if it's not
accidental as you said it's it's related
to mental action but
um the important thing to see is that
like that mental
action isn't just like it's
it's a simple failure to protect the
same thing that you were already doing.
It's not even like
some secret information that you didn't
have like oh unfortunately they told you
how to build up the mindfulness but
nobody taught you how to maintain it as
if it's a different thing. It's
literally the same context that you've
been maintain maintaining. It's still
there but you like we said before
carelessly choose to just emphasize the
other stuff. Um so but what what what
are the things
that would
um take you in that opposite direction?
That's it.
Distraction. Mhm. Company. Mhm. Work.
Yeah. Okay. Those are kind of the
external things. But as we said mentally
even before you give in Mhm. by body
speech he nurses.
he nurses.
Yeah. Exactly. Because Hindu says as as
you read in the sutras it's like it's a
um weakeners of wisdom or like they they
uh constrict the mind and that
constriction is 100% exactly the opposite direction
is 100% exactly the opposite direction
of the broader perspective that uh
mindfulness is.
So you don't even have that's that's
exactly why even without breaking the
precepts you would still be able to
um emphasize the wrong direction and and
pretty much willingly wear away your
mindfulness because yeah restlessness
doubt like let's say you develop some
clarity about some aspect of dharma and you saw
about some aspect of dharma and you saw
that oh what the the dharma No, the
practice is to not act out of painful
feelings. But before that was just
theory. That was just information. Now
you're seeing it on that experiential
level. You have that clarity
developed. But then
uh doubts come up, questions come up
about things that you know are secondary
things that you know are that you know
that what matters is not acting out of
unpleasant feelings. and you know that
any type of actually relevant wisdom
would come out of that wouldn't come out
of you clarifying um abstract ideas but
still the pressure is just too much for
you to to stick to what you already know
is right. Um,
so it's it's basically that. It's it's
it's a a simple choice
a a simple choice
to not protect the same thing that that
was already there. And like you were
saying before, you kind of know like if
somebody were to to just suddenly, I
don't know, break into your room and ask
you a question at that moment, which is
a wholesome thing to
do to go through with that doubt or to
see that as a painful feeling that's
pressuring you and not act out of it.
You would give the right
answer. But uh yeah, so it's it's that's
why it's it's basically gratuitous. You
might not be asking yourself that though
necessarily. Exactly. So that's the
problem. like like um you know, but then
you choose to to pretty much put aside
the clarity that you yourself have. So
it's a it's um it's a selfinduced
uh problem. Let's say in the same way
that the development of mindfulness
cannot be cannot happen accidentally.
It's not that that you know you you just
get put in the right environment and
suddenly it develops on its own. There
is no way for that to to build up unless
you have been doing the right things.
You may not recognize it in hindsight
that you were doing the right things
because maybe you haven't had the right
information sufficiently or or you
haven't reflected on it enough. So you
would you wouldn't be able to do it
again. But factually it's something that
you would have had to work for let's say
um because the direction of pressure the
direction of
hindrances is uh like nobody will
accidentally stop giving into that because every
stop giving into that because every
reward that that anybody can conceivably
know of lies in that direction lies in
the direction of acting out.
So without faith, without some degree of
let's say higher motivation, there is no
way that you can just endure that pain
and maintain the clarity of feelings,
the body, all the things this talk
about. So how do you know if you're
acting out of hindrances? Because
obviously this is not something that
would be externally defined by as in the
way the precepts are like you know just
don't do this and you won't be acting
out of hindises. Obviously it's it's uh
only to a certain extent which is the
extent of the eight precepts. If you do
those things, you're acting out of
innocence. But beyond that,
um, is there a way to know
internally what is going to be rooted in
the hindrance and what is not.
You could you could check whether that
perspective is
established that we've been talking
about. Mhm.
since it's a completely since it's the
opposite direction.
um
the the clarity there in that
perspective
um and what you're being presented with
where that is also included.
Um well but it it is going to be
included because that's what how
mindfulness works like when it's there
everything is included. So,
so how how would you be able to know
that this action that's being presented
to you right now by your own mind that
it's going to take you away from this
clarity. In other words, that it's a
hindrance. Even if you don't because
it's you you don't even need to use the
I classify it into oh it's this type of
hindrance, it's that type of hindrance.
you will be able to just directly see
this is the opposite direction of what
what what I've cultivated. So how would
you know? [Music]
Well, what comes to mind is if I was to
abstain from following action, it would
be unpleasant.
Yes, that's one way you could look at
it. So, anything
that the mind
feels apprehensive
when you even tease the option of saying no
you even tease the option of saying no
to it. Um, that's already shows you that
there's probably gratification and
infatuation involved with that action.
So, because see that is what makes the
mind unwilling to
basically have the clarity that you
yourself want to develop. It's the fact
that like when you don't have that
like when you don't have that
clarity, you can be having the same
thoughts and the same reflections and
the same encouragements to for the mind
and uh it just ignores them. doesn't
listen to them and it insists in being
concerned instead with sight, sounds,
smells, taste, touches, worries about
the past, concerns about the future.
So it's when you
basically push it in any direction where
like actually you would be able to know
in advance like oh this will if I do
this the mind will become
um agitated. Yeah. Or or you could also
say the mind won't listen. You can
simply put like when you have a dog and
you know you kind of have it on a close
leash and it's listening to you and it's
kind of obedient and then you let it go
a little bit and like the more you let
it go, the harder it's going to be. You
see, like if you let it go, depending on
the attitude that it has, depending on
the behavior that it's showing, you can
see like what that engagement will
result in. If the dog is calm and you
let it walk, well, that's fine. But if
you see that it's already getting in
that kind of excitement mode and you
actually let it go, what what you will
see is um it's going to be three times
harder to bring it back afterwards.
Yeah. And and that's what you have to
recognize. you have to stop being
concerned with like the kind of external
definitions of what is allowable and
what is not allowable. Um if something
you if you see that at that
moment not yesterday, not tomorrow, not
10 years ago, at that
moment that dog is kind of getting into
that mode of agitation towards this
action that might be externally
praiseworthy and externally um you know
considered whatever virtuous then you
don't do it. Because at that like that
what what is a hindrance and what is not
a hindrance is going to be determined by
your own mind not by you and your kind
of
uh classification and and your
preference of of um that's why it's
it's in a way it is a fundamental truth
or fundamental uh principle but at the
same time that doesn't mean it's public.
It is to be experienced individually by
the wise because only in relation to
your own mind can you know what is a
hindrance and what is not. What is
wholesome and what is unh wholesome.
Yeah. So it's universal but subjective.
Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. So it's it's you
cannot make a a kind of again apart from
the precepts you cannot make a list of
universal that are always leading you
astray. Well, that would be then the
research. But within that, um, yeah, you
have to determine from within the
situation that you're in, which includes
which feeling is present, what mood is
going on there, which which are
precisely the satana, by the way, those
you you want to keep an eye on because
that from day to day change. Yeah,
that's what I was thinking. Even if you
could come up with the perfect list that
is tailored specifically to your mind
and your mind's tendencies, it'll just
it doesn't matter because it changes
from day to day. So, so it's like you
can make a list of things that in the
past would have led to hindrances and
you may well overlook that your attitude
of list building at that very moment is
rooted in restlessness and it's
something or doubt or doubt and it's
something that the mind is with that
same agitation engaging with. So it's
it's it can only be seen presently and
uh in that peripheral dimension of like
yeah how what is this going to do for to
my mind like is it going to make it more
obedient or less obedient just in that
general level you don't even have to
think in terms of like um oh how does
this action relate to you know the body
or feelings or something like that is it
is this animal going to listen to me
less and be concerned with the world as a
and be concerned with the world as a
result of me letting it do this. And
even if those things that it's concerned
with are not as bad as the things that
you let go through the precepts, let's
say, um it's still the fact that it is
going to become disobedient, that is bad
in and of itself. It doesn't matter if
it becomes disobedient for like, you
know, things that are that are that
other people may regard as fine. And
that's why the sas would say that um a
noble disciple would be would be
um basically hindered from from
progressing further if they become
overly engaged with talk, sleep and uh
work which none of them are against the
precepts. Uh but it's the fact that they
kind of
um again push the push the mind into
that mode where it's not going to listen
to you and where it's not going to be
pliable for developing the context and
uh and um and and taking it into
directions that it has to go which is
dispassion, relinquishment, sessation.
That alone is a problem that it's that
it's going to make the mind disobedient.
So that needs to be once the precepts
are established, the standard needs to
be upgraded to that much more general
level of like leading to pliability of
mind, leading away from pliability of
mind. And and
um it's
it's it's important as well to see
that the attitude of denying everything
the attitude of denying everything
that's another trap actually. Like it's
not that if you say no to everything,
you're going to make it that much more
pliable. Like if I if I could just say
no to everything, then oh well,
everything's fixed, right? Well, if only
we're that easy. It's
it's because in and of itself that
engagement of saying no to things that
very much can be in aversion, which is
another one of the hindrances.
So
um it's it's a it's a kind of balancing
act almost and uh you'll have to not
even trial and error because trial and
error kind of implies that you that you
will find like a fixed answer at a
certain point but it's not you don't
find an answer to to what is a hindrance
and what isn't and how to calm the mind.
You just understand the broader
principle that you're able to apply in
each individual
circumstance as if
um you that
um training of the mind
um or making it more pliable I suppose.
Is that only discerned
through like does it have to be
discerned through feeling? So it's not
like I can just think about it
abstractly.
That has to be Yeah. to know what choice
to make. It has to be felt. Mhm.
Basically, yeah. You have to feel it
quote unquote at that moment. You have
to feel cuz that's the thing. The mind
is is
um like it's not something that you
would be able to overlook or let's say
it's it's you would be certainly be able
to overlook it but it's not something
that can be actually absent from your
experience. It is there. It's just that
if you don't look that direction
like just a simple kind
of glimpse of how is the mind kind
of reacting to this or or what kind of
um disposition or behavior is it showing
when it looks in that
direction. And uh it's that feeling
that's felt at that moment. If it's if
it's uh as as the sutas would say the
joy and pleasure on account
of mundane
things that's what you shouldn't
cultivate. He said that pleasure should
be feared should be uh shunned should be
avoided not the external sense objects
but the feeling that you see on the
level of the mind when it's inclining
towards those things. That's what's has
to be
avoided. And on the other hand, if
there's no feeling there that there's no
feeling of pleasure of on that mental
level, uh when the mind is is
uh when the mind is is
um let's say I don't know the classic
example, it wants to go for a
walk but there's no like kind of
obsessive sense of pleasure associated
with it. You don't really care that much
if you don't do it either. then uh you
have to see oh wait well I I don't have
to say no to
this because if you if you do then you
if you do say no to it it means you're
emphasizing something other than the
actual discernment of the mind you're
just using your preconceived notions of
oh I shouldn't do this because such and
such um
um
so and on the other hand as well
um with uh aversion
Like if you if you realize
um let's say avoid avoiding certain
types of
discomfort like when is that actually
aversion and when is it
just acting according to intentions?
Well, that's that's how you would know
like is the mind
internally upset and agitated about
this? Like is it is it going to kind of
rebel and complain if I don't let it
avoid this? Well, then you might want to
think twice about
um giving into that intention of of
avoidance. If it doesn't really care,
then okay, then why would you be like as
as those aesthetics were doing, like you
know, subjecting themselves to
um pain, bodily pain in any way they
could imagine
it. It's kind of like thinking you can
train a dog. I mean, when it does
something wrong, you hate it. But then
it's not doing anything wrong and you
think, well, might as well hate it. It
It will make it more obedient.
Yeah. Not that you're anxious confusing
the dog. Well, it will fear you, but it
won't go well,
not for the right reason. Yeah. But now
it won't be obedient. It just won't do.
It won't go anywhere, so to say. Even
where you would want it to go.
Yeah, but if you only hit it and it is
factually doing something wrong, then
the message what is wrong would be
clearer to the dog. Then then then if
that's being clouded by just a slap here
and there, they'll just be confused like
what's wrong with this now. Yeah. So the
thing is that's why it's then important
to to put aside your notions of of
what's right and wrong and base
everything upon the mind. like
discernment of um the present mental
state, the present mood, is it affected
with greed, is it affected with
aversion, is it effective with delusion?
Um
because well, as as we've discussed
before, that's how you would also
overcome satasa. That's how you would
cease to emphasize any sort of
preconceived notions of what of sense of
duty or sense of um like being being
needing to to adhere to some kind of
external standard of of behavior and
instead everything would be
automatically oriented by that vision
of how is the mind
inclining in relation to this action at
this moment. Mhm. Not not in an abstract
sense. I I was kind of thinking about
I I was kind of thinking about
throughout this discussion um when a
moly would say
like if uh it doesn't matter kind of if
you can handle it if the mind can handle
it that is yeah it kind of ties into
like oh yeah it's fine if I do this but
then that's not really what you should
be focusing on. Yeah. Yeah. Like what is
the consequence going to be for the mind
when you do this which is not
necessarily going to be like
a s it's not going to be as
uh well within your control. Yeah. Like
like we said like we said just now the
greater issue comes from the fact that
the mind if it's factually developed
some degree of perspective you may not
even feel the pain right away because
factually the mind becomes immovable. So
then um you will realize only afterwards like
um you will realize only afterwards like
when when the oh wait I'm I'm sitting in
the spit of burning coals again. Uh so
you you but that that's the thing you can
you but that that's the thing you can
see already even before you go through
with it. You factually can see that is
where the mind will end up.
It may not be immediate cuz if it were
immediate well you probably wouldn't go through
well you probably wouldn't go through
with it. But it's precisely because it's
kind of like far away and you think
like, "Oh, no, no. I'll I'll kind of
I'll get back on track way before I end
up in that direction." And that's why
you let it go and and you don't realize
like it's it's like a snowball. So just
one little bit is is enough
to just keep keep rolling. You could
stop yourself factually, but why?
Who on in their right mind would like
start exciting a dog that's twice
heavier than them to want to go in the
opposite direction where they want them
to be in. Even if they can't stop it,
why would they
risk being dragged to where they don't
want to go?
And what you said about the
paramas and seeing well seeing giving up
your idea
of this external thing is how I train my
mind I would say it's more
well more so than giving up what you
think is this external thing that you
are doing is more about questioning what
you think external means
cuz like oh obviously I'm not doing
those things failing to see well there
must be something you are doing in that
in that way otherwise you would have
seen yeah because external of course um
you know that that's what we always end
up coming back to like this uh common
notion of of rights and rituals. That's
like oh the obviously external thing and
then to some extent you realize that
yeah if if you have if you're half wise
you realize yeah that's that's not where
the training lies. But like what is
actually external? External could very
well be still on the level of
um internal quote unquote practices of
like the the the the ways that you think
you need to be u reflecting or
contemplating or whatever or the ways
that you think you should be watching
your intentions or um directing the mind
like this or directing the mind like
that. All of that would be made external
if you don't see the actual inclination
of the mind at that moment. Yes. Like
you might have a sense of duty for
example built up in the course of your
life and now you are in a situation when
where when when where nothing properly
external is insisting that you should
perform that duty but you still do it
because you regard it as duty. Yeah. But
even on a more accurate level, even if
externally you're not it's it's not
nothing that anybody anybody else can
see. Uhhuh. It's fully mental. Yes. And
uh and you would it would still be an
external silaba. It would be an external
sense of duty of could be anything.
Could be I don't know reflecting on
death or every day I have to be you know
reflecting on the the drawbacks of
sensuality. Yeah. every single day and
those things are you see you're not even
seeing um like how is the mind inclining
is it actually working where is it
taking me you just take take on this
kind of repetitive
um yeah performance of a of a certain
thing and then you get sick for half a
week or for a week and you can't do your
particular exercises and then you feel
that you are not fulfilling your duty as
a mom and then that becomes unpleasant.
Yeah. And so the whole thing just goes
downhill because from the start was
already wrong. Yeah. So you have to see
on the acute internal presently arisen
level um as you you have to use that as a
um as you you have to use that as a
standard for what needs to be done and
what doesn't need to be done and then
you would realize it it works both ways.
It works both in the sense that
sometimes you might be overdoing it like
sometimes you might be the mind is
already in the direction of you know
clarity and context but you keep pushing
it and prodding it with these
reflections that already serve a purpose
and uh which would be like well that
would then become a restlessness for
example you just don't know when it's
okay or it could work the other way
around as well that you know you you
think like often with the kind of um
idea that that meditation is like this
session that you do during the day. So
it will work both ways. So during the
session you think that you have to be
focusing every moment. You don't realize
like where when the mind is factually
um already clear about the context. You
don't need to keep repeating it anymore.
And also you you would think that when
the session ends that you can just do
whatever you want. Yeah. Failing to see
that actually no you you the mind you
can't press pause on the mind. No but
I've done my duty. I've done my hour in
the morning and I've done my Buddha in
the evening. So what happens during the
rest of the day doesn't matter. Exactly.
So and if you do two hours in the
morning then for the rest of the day
you're fine. Yeah. Yeah.
So at any given time you will have to be
clear about this and this might this
very reflection might become mechanical
at some point the reflection of where
the intention is and how the mind is
planning towards things that that will
become your external practice at some
point but uh you always have a chance if
if you have been keeping the virtue if
you have been keeping the senses
straight and you and you know that you
have to be self honest at some point it
will land on you that Oh, wait. I'm
doing this now with this insane external
sense of duty. Yeah.
And then you would see, oh, okay. So,
that's where the mind is inclining. It
wasn't like everything else that I was
assuming to be the inclination of the
mind was secondary. It was this very
pressure that was directing me to do
this. That's what that's where it was.
Well, that's kind of the thing. And it's
kind of the ironic bit
is all of those things that you'll be
doing wrongly to address the issue, you
are doing precisely so as not to address
the issue. Yeah. Yeah. You you so as to
ignore the state of the mind that's
right there. The the because see not
acting out of restlessness is painful.
And and so that's what you're doing
right then and there. And uh sure you
might somebody asks you what what am I
doing? Yeah. Yeah. I'm trying to not
like that of the hindrances. But uh yeah
what what you what the mind says it's
doing and what it's actually doing is
two different things. And you need to be
able to discern the latter and not go by
just what the mind kind of what you
initially when you ask yourself what am
I doing the first answer that comes
that's not actually the intention when
we talk about reflecting on intentions I
think we clarify that before
that usually you might think it's like
the reasons the reasoning behind
like the explanation behind this action
But no, you would be more accurate to
say like what would happen if I just
stop this. That's what that's what that's
this. That's what that's what that's
where the that would that kind of
reflection would indirectly reveal what
present inclination there is. What what
happens if I don't do
it? And uh that's what would determine
the extent of mindfulness as well. when
you realize oh whether I do it or don't
do it it doesn't matter the clarity is
there and then you need to protect it
then if
it's you know in the direction of
sensuality in the direction of aversion
even if at that moment it it won't be
int the intense aversion that you or
intense sensuality that you give gave up
initially you have to realize well but
even a little bit is going to start
taking me back to where I worked so hard
to to get away from so why would I go
back there and that now becomes the way
another way for you to strengthen
strengthen the mindfulness even more. So
just simply by abstaining from those
actions the perspective will grow even
stronger
basically. But also if if you see
that the mind's inclination, you could
just as well ask like how will accepting
this um affect the mind
um affect the mind
as opposed to like it
would like you could ask yourself, oh
will I get upset or will the mind get
upset if I refuse to accept this? But
then if you see it, even if you ask
yourself just like, "Oh, but even how
would the mind where would the mind go
if I accept this?" You would see the
same. It's just kind of the
different aspect of the same
intention. Sorry. Well, the mind would
present some option. Mhm.
and entertaining, let's say, like
mentally like thinking how where
accepting would lead would reveal it
just as much as thinking about where
refusing that would lead. Uhhuh. I see
what you mean. just the different but
the thing is without some perspective
when you would entertain accepting it
you would just be overwhelmed by the
well the pleasure that's offered then
like basically falling into yeah you
would you would see the thing is
um if you question yourself like you
might have already accepted it mentally
so that's why more often than not
contemplating what what happens if I
just don't do it what happens if I this
thing I never get to experience this
thing ever again.
Then that would reveal to you because
the direction of welcoming and accepting
it's kind of already bound with with and
it's also already bound with um a
diminishing perspective. So then to the
extent that you already went in that
direction, you won't be able to be clear
about the fact that you are going in
that direction. Like it it kind of uh
muddles your own self-awareness. In
other words, you can't be that's why you
can't engage in sensuality mindfully
like having perspective over your
sensuality. That's that's two
incompatible things. Sensuality means
not having perspective. So more often
than not if you ask
yourself oh not even just bodily physically um
oh not even just bodily physically um
kind of giving in what happens if I just
don't think about this and you would
already see like oh wait so there was a
compulsion there and uh if if if you
were going by your again your
preconceived ideas of what's right and
wrong you might have thought oh well
this is not the precepts this is this is
is even like kind of praiseworthy action
like I'm helping other people or
something and you would have emphasized
that rather than um clearly like the
mind is is itching and this is the way
that it's scratching itself right now.
Yeah.
And but yeah, like when you have um
inclinations of like over overly denying
things like with kind of
selfmortification and you ask yourself
like, oh, so what would happen if I
stopped doing these aesthetic practices?
Would I feel a threat, a sense of threat
to my
And uh and that's what that's what you
would see in the sutas like when
when they saw that the Buddha ate milk
rice and they were outraged like you
know like he he he completely just fell
from the practice and then you realize
wait so but that's another compulsion so
that cannot possibly be the direction
where actual peace lies.
It might be less uh blinding than uh
sensuality just because
um relaxing is always easier than
tightening simply because of that. But
uh to the extent that the mind is is to
to the extent that there's concern to
the extent that there's need to the
extent that there's dependence it's a
problem and it's not what I is. So you
would realize oh if if I cannot
[Music] uh survive without denying things that
uh survive without denying things that
are not even greedy aversion and
delusion in
themselves that's that's a sign of the
same
hindrances would this also apply to when
the mind starts to leap up renunciation
as it says it is. That's sort of it
doesn't at first but eventually the one
progresses and sees it as pleasant but
then it's about
how how close or yeah refining that
pronunciation so it's not just this kind
of I'm just going to give things up for
the sake of them for the sake of okay
well I'm not going to
just eat with a spoon anymore. Yeah.
Yeah. Just uh uh just give in to that
um pressure along the same lines. Yeah.
If it's at the actual renunciation on
that level, you would see that it's if
you renounce the external things, it
would be coming from the other direction. It
be coming from the other direction. It
would be coming from the direction of
seeing how that will affect the mind.
You won't you won't be giving things up
just because you heard that there was
this great monk who also
did or also gave these things up. You
would see directly for this mind giving
this up is going to lead to more awesome
states. But that's not usually what
people do. They they do it on they have
the inspiration
uh to give things up which is good but
then they judge what has to be given up
by all sorts of external u
criteria. It sounds silly but generally
it often is like oh I heard that there
was such and such and that's what he did
so let me do it too. And uh there's no
direct discernment of of like okay but
is this
actually increasing my
perspective is this
actually do I see that on account of
doing this uh the mind doesn't incline
to sensual thoughts anymore or am I just
like occupying myself with this other
stuff and that's why the sensual
thoughts arise don't arise
anymore like I'm just occupying with I
don't know traveling around and living
in the forest and because I always have
something to do and the next thing to
take care of and worry about that's why
I don't have sensual thoughts coming up
not because you know you actually set up
the renunciation properly and then the
mind is is generally turned away from
that whole
domain. Yeah. So in connection with this
Can you be hindered by just one
hindrance? Sometimes people ask this
question like what's your what's your
dominant hindrance? Having the
impression like okay so all the other
four hindrances I'm sort of there that's
just this one. Would that be an accurate
discernment? maybe center
maybe center
stage. Um there is a kind of tone. Yeah.
Particular. Yes. That you can identify.
But can there be like is it possible for
someone that can it be like okay there's
just this hindrance center states and
and the other four they're just not
there now.
Um well you would be relating to that
hindrance in some way. So it could be
with the same entrance or it could be
with a different entrance.
Well the thing is of course
um they are five. Yes.
So in a way you you can you can have you
can recognize specific manifestations of
hindrances. But um it works the same way as what we
But um it works the same way as what we
said before with the clarity of
mindfulness. Like it's not um you could
say you have liability to clarity or
liability to mleness
like inclination towards clarity or
inclination towards mleness and
inclination towards clarity
is the opposite of hindrances. Therefore
it doesn't matter what specifically that
clarity is
uh directed towards. The point is there
is the broader sense of clarity there
and the same same with the hindrances.
It doesn't matter which one of them
specifically or at least the determining
factor is not going to be which one of
them is there. Exactly. It's the fact
that you're liable. Mhm. To have well
that you're effectively hinders. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So then whichever like for
someone who gives into sensuality
um if bad things happen to them they
will be that much more prone to get
angry. Mhm. If
uh you know there is some sort of threat
to something that they value they'll be
that much of course because that's what
sensuality is valuing and being attached
to things. they'll be that much more of
a liability to be worried and concerned
about it and they don't have stimul the
stimulation that they're used to uh then
the whole lazy laziness and
interpreter comes up. So you would see
the same same uh works the other way
around like when somebody has been
giving into aversion and and uh or even
sadness, depression and all these
things. What is it that they look
for? What is it that they look for to
uplift their mood? It's sensuality
which is which is where the mood went
down to be I want to be. Yeah.
And if you've
been giving into doubts and and uh
concerns and
worries, the same thing happens.
Like the
first promise of peace that you're going
to see is, oh, let me just find some
pleasant sense object to engage with to
calm the mind down.
And uh that's that's not the type of
confidence that you want. Uhhuh. You
keep yourself within. Yeah. Like you you
Well, that's the thing. You kind of
uh pushing away the specific
manifestation by doing this action. Like
so momentarily it it might um covered up
but the overall liability is being
increased as a result of you giving it.
So next thing comes up you get bored of
whatever pleasant object that was and uh
you will find oh wait actually they
didn't solve the problem.
Yeah that boredom is also on the level
of the hind restlessness.
Oh yeah boredom like uh what would
happen if I think I said that before.
What would happen if you're thrown into
solitary confinement after you've been
indulging in sensuality and distractions
for a whole day
and uh what will how would that compare
to when you haven't when you have been
restrained? You'd see the boredom would
hit you way way harder if you've because
it's exactly like
abruptly cutting off the the like a
train that's been moving in uh I don't
know 200 hour and suddenly stopping it.
So the ben would almost not even
manifest. It would just be like
restlessness like you would still have
to calm down from your essential
engagements and and only then well yeah
but the boredom whichever way you take
it whether it's restlessness whether
it's boredom the whole point is uh
you're going to be liable to it
precisely because of the sensuality
even though you might see it as a
completely separate thing you might not
even see the connection no that was
precisely what I was trying to get at so
the whole idea that you can just be like
hinded by one hind and which is
unrelated to the other four. That's
quite a wrong understanding of the
hindrance.
I had a a
question just rel I guess in some ways
related um it was about contentment and
so developing contentment would help to
unhinder unhind unhinder one and um it's
it's based off of this suta where like
where S put is giving a discourse about
at first going forth is difficult and
then contentment is difficult to develop
and so and so on. And so I was wondering
um maybe what this
contentment that Sar is referring to is
maybe it could be elaborated on but um
and whether it's actually just what
we've been discussing here as well about
training training the mind and
um keeping a mindfulness established and
that yeah in some way you're going to
become careless when you're discontent
with what's offered. That's how I kind
of see it, but I'm not sure if
that's completely what's being referred
to. So, what what would what what would
people think contentment is in the right
sense? If it's cuz um
um
some marginal amount of contentment
people might think comes from the world
and sensuality, but what would be the
difference between the contentment that
comes from Rightly changing the
mind and what will be the difference.
Well, I guess most obvious thing would
be that the first would be dependent on
cir by definition dependent on the
circumstances. So you'd recognize, oh, if this is taken
So you'd recognize, oh, if this is taken
away or burns down or Yeah.
dies, how would I be left with them
then? Yeah. Or how would that affect
them? Yeah. Whereas the other one would
basically well be completely independent of all of
well be completely independent of all of
that by definition. Yeah. So it's
independent of external circumstances.
Of course, anybody who is inclined
towards spirituality would recognize it
as a good thing. But uh it it has to
ultimately be independent from eternal
circumstances as well. From
deterioration of your own faculties,
from arising of pressure on a mental
level because that's another
circumstance. independent of unpleasant
feelings, independent of unpleasant
moods, independent of um whatever mental
uh things can come up regardless of your
wish for them not to come up. So when uh
contentment depends on having a certain
feeling for that
matter, that's not the right type of
contentment because pleasant feeling is
impermanent as the Buddha says. So um
the right type of contentment is when it
doesn't even matter when you feel this
pleasure. That's the only one that will
survive everything basically. And the
um when that says that it's it's
difficult to to find contentment. Well,
it's it's it's because the contentment that
it's it's because the contentment that
you have to find lies precisely in the
direction that initially will be felt as
discontent like
um giving up acting out of pressure even
though you've already gone forth as as
says like you already went forth but
despite going forth you still haven't
derived your contentment.
So because sometimes people might think
like oh if I just become a monk and just
give everything up I'll be happy with
nothing or something like that. But it's
way more subtle than that because you
still will have the tendency to
internally act out of pressure and seek
to seek the contentment on the level of
managing your feelings again like doing
doing things that that um to get rid of
pain. And for as long as that remains
your your hope of achieving contentment
um fundamentally externally you might be
more restrained but internally you still
maintain the same principle which
ironically is what makes you discontent.
The need to
um have conditions be a certain way even
internally. That's what makes you
discontent because deep down you know
like it will deteriorate and deep down
you know that you have to protect it. So
from that point of view compared to the
actual contentment it's not even it's
not even contentment because it comes
with the with the implicit
um worry and and implicit kind of
knowledge that it could be taken away at
any time.
So uh arriving at the right contentment
will require to some extent
um enduring discontent but that
discontent you have to see that it's not
because of the
restraint. Uh it's not because you're
not giving into the pressure that you're
discontented. You're discontented simply
because you're resisting the pain of not
giving into the pressure. Once you stop
resisting the pain and not giving into
the pressure, that's exactly what the
contentment is, not resisting because
you ask yourself, why am I
resisting and you realize there's no
there's no um justification for it. So
if you give that up, which of course
sounds easier than it actually is, uh
you realize, oh yeah, I was discontent
because I myself was making myself so
through my own um wrong way of attending
things basically still implying to some
extent that I need to find a solution to
this pain whereas the attitude of needing to
pain whereas the attitude of needing to
find a solution is the reason why the
pain is a problem in the first place.
And then virtue would be purified
because there would be no way of acting
up. Well, only then. Yeah. So before
that you would be would be pleasant of a
more virtuous life in a sense. Yeah.
Still to some extent you would still
be in valuing certainly the things of
the world like you would be
um giving them up because you hope that
you will get something in return later
on. you don't see directly here and now.
Um as the Buddhist said the like
sensuality takes time but the dharma is
presently evident and you wouldn't see
in that presently evident sense why
giving these things up is already
better. You would be thinking like oh
later on something will happen that will
kind of make all of this worthwhile or
something like that. And that's another
sensuality. It's within the pain you
have to find the escape and that's when
it it will be independent of anything
any circumstance any any deterioration
of
conditions and I think the says once
you've uh do find contaminant then then
uh it wouldn't take long there's no
what's hard then practicing ing in line
with the teaching, right? Yeah. But for
someone who practices in line with the
teaching would Yeah.
would Yeah.
Well, you that that connects with what
we've been saying before like you might
actually be contented factually like the
mind has developed the clarity. It sees
things that
u go against the practice, sees them as
as unpleasant, as not worth it, as as
uh yeah, as a as a charcoal pit as the
sutas would say. And yet still
practicing the dharma isn't
automatic. It's it's not a it's not a
guarantee. It doesn't follow that just
because you're contented, you would
automatically practice the night of the
devil, which sounds um kind of
counterintuitive, but factually that's
that's how it is. Like there's that sut
where where it says um a monk might
might enter the first Janna and uh
somebody might think, oh, he will never
go back to sensual pleasures. And then
the gives assimilates like when uh you
know like when the when it's been really
dry and then dust starts accumulating
and then it rains and then somebody
thinks oh this dust will never come back
and uh and it goes all the way to the
forj and uh it's it's that is the
factual most accurate contentment that
you could arrive at and uh and yet it
says but even then after achieving that
somebody might even disro and the monk
and that's what the this is what he did.
Um now of course that doesn't mean that
uh that doesn't mean that the contendant
that we're referring to like factually
it has to be outside of
sensuality. Um most of the time what
people would call Janna isn't actually
outside of sity. So that's even deeper
problem there. But even if you reach the
real deal um yeah the mind is
is still in a way precisely because of
you having reached that greater
perspective. you might
disregard everything else that you had
to do in order to arrive at it because
it feels like oh well the mind is asuta
says the elephant that's now invincible
in battle
um that that can take everything like
swords spears and and everything without
reacting and so you send it into
battle but it wasn't actually ready and
then it dies
So there comes a point you can't lose
mindfulness. Well that point would come
already like yeah the point when you
can't lose mindfulness is when you have
samadi that's that factually is like
even if you want to you can't lose it.
The problem is if
you factually without losing it do
certain things, you will suddenly find
that you lost it. Let's put it that way.
Like you were not losing it while you
were doing those things or at least it
didn't feel like you
were, but then when you turn around you
realize actually it wasn't there. That's
how it works because it's that indirect
dimension. It's that indirect kind of
um yeah the kind of ultimate background
of your experience. So
uh you would start taking it for granted
basically that you would you would start
doing things thinking like oh well yeah
the Hindus are gone it doesn't matter.
Um but it's it's that gradual kind of
inclining as the Buddha would say what
what you
incline what you frequently think and
ponder about that's what the mind
inclines to. So it's a gradual kind
of bit by bit pushing it back in that
direction and then you will find oh
actually it is now it's more on that
side than the right side that I had it
in initially.
That's one thing that people would
really struggle to understand when we
say like the in order to enter the first
Janna you factually have to
uh give up even the liability to the
five hindrances not just like specific
manifestations because then it would
sound like also you're saying you have
to basically become an arat in order to
enter the first J. But the thing
is, yeah, the liability to the
hindrances is factually gone at that
time whether you like it or not. But
that doesn't mean that uh they will not
come
back. Because if you incline the mind,
if you if
you give in to the things that at that
time don't feel like they're a problem,
the hindrances will return.
Not immediately, but they will return.
And there's
no removing the liability to the
liability of the injustices. It's just
that they are well that's really staying
there by by staying there by staying in
the state where you're not liable to
hindrances then uh then yeah you would
any inclination to turn the mind back
towards the hindrances would be gone. So
then you wouldn't fall away from it out
of the unh wholesome reasons. you would
fall away from it just
because of circumstantial reasons. But
not like someone who's not free from
sensuality who falls away because
factually they start like the the
fedters and stuff get them to incline
the mind in the opposite direction